we hear the words
natural and synthetic
all the time when talking about food,
medicine, clothes
and other things. but what do they mean?
if you took a poll
most people would tell you that natural
has to do with their juice cleanse
organic groceries, yoga and other healthy activities
but for synthetic they'll warn you of toxins
scary chemicals and mean confusing
chemistry teachers
with all these charged emotions it's not
surprising that a lot of people equate
these words with good and bad. but this discounts
everything chemistry has to offer
society, so we need to change this view
natural simply means made by nature, the
same benevolent force that brings us
deadly viruses and toxic blowfish
which looks strangely similar. synthetic means
made by humans who save lives with
antibiotics
and synthetic microbes that eat up the
oil from a tanker spill. now that we've
decoupled these words from good and bad
let's look at something both nature and humans
make. a vitamin is something we must
consume in small amounts
in order for our cells to keep normal
function and metabolism
most plants and animals make these on
their own but somewhere along biological
evolution
a few mammals lost the ability so we
have to eat them
take vitamin C. for thousands of years
we've gotten this from fruit
but with modern science we can identify
the structure of this and other
compounds
and make them ourselves. the question is
are they the same? to answer that
let's look at how a vitamin works. a
vitamin has just the right shape to fit
into an
active site of an enzyme and make
interactions that turn on the enzyme
like a lock and key. and just as it
doesn't matter who makes your key
as long as it's the right shape for the
lock, same goes for the vitamin
that's why any molecule that these
specific atoms
arranged in this way is vitamin C
nature makes this just fine, always has
but when nature does chemistry
it is limited to the normal pH and
temperature inside a living organism
so it has to use big bulky molecules
to do blind chemistry. when we do
chemistry
we can use any exotic compounds and
conditions we want to build
any molecule we want, and even though the pathways
are different the end product is the
exact same
molecule. so the bioactivity of a
molecule can not depend on how it came
to be
an enzyme simply can't tell the
difference. furthermore
it is often cheaper and easier to
synthesize these in mass quantities
than to have to extract and purify from
natural sources
so if we want to keep the growing global population
healthy and well-fed, we have to get over
the idea
that science looks like this, because
science
looks like this